A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Taryn Higashi FA683
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Taryn Higashi
1973-2009
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Higashi, Taryn
FA683
4.56 Cubic Feet 12 letter document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2019:180 and 2019:154.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reports, grant-related materials, and correpondence from Taryn Higashi's roles within the Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation Unit (HRIC) at the Ford Foundation.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged "as received" from the Ford Foundation.
- Cuba: 1998 Report to the Ford Foundation (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Community Foundations - Ford Initiatives, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ford Foundation's Program in the Changing Role of Women - Information Paper, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Community Organizing - National Organizers Alliance (NOA), 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- NGO Group for the Convention on the Rights of Migrant Workers, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Criminal Justice and Immigration Reform: Bridging the Gaps, Opportunities and Risks, Report of the Convening of Immigrants' Rights and Criminal Justice Advocates, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Detention Post-9/11, American Bar Association Publications, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  Georgetown Journal on Poverty Law and Policy Volume IX, Winter 2002, Number 1
  A Legal Guide for INS Detainees: Petitioning for Release from Indefinite Detention, American Bar Association
  A Legal Guide for INS Detainees: Actions Brought Against INS Or Other Law Enforcement Officials for Personal Injury or Property Damage or Loss, American Bar Association
  A Legal Guide for INS Detainees, American Bar Association
- Racing Toward "Big Brother:" Computer Verification, National ID Cards, and Immigration Control, National Council of La Raza, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Journal of the East European Law Center, Volume 7, Nos. 3-4, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Facing the Past: The Romanian Lustration Law, Mihaela Rosen
- Fenton Communications' Final Report and Evaluation of the 9/11 Coordinated Communications Initiative, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Human Rights in Africa: The Role of Donors and International Human Rights NGOs, A Survey, Ian Gary - Memo for Ford, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Internally Displaced Persons (IDPs), 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Indigenous Mexican Migrants in the US: Building Bridges Between Researchers and Community Leaders, University of California, Santa Cruz, 2002 October 11-12 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Causes and Trends in Migrant Deaths along the U.S.-Mexico Border, Karl Eschbach, Jacqueline Hagan, and Nestor Rodriguez, Center for Immigration Research, Univeristy of Houston, 2001 March (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Mexico, U.S. Articles by Douglas Massey, 1993-2003 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Indonesian Migrant Workers: Systematic Abuse at Home and Abroad, Suzanne Siskel, 2002 June 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Network News, The National Network of Grantmakers, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Workshop on Alternative Futures, Refugee Studies Centre of the University of Oxford, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Public Interest Projects (PIP) - General, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Police Foundation, 2005-2009 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Gay and Lesbian Concerns: Past, Current, and Possible Future Programming by the Ford Foundation - Memo, Priscilla Hayner, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Economic, Social and Cultural Rights Project (PRODESC), 2007 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Refugee Consortium of Kenya - Tie Off, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- A Closer Look at the Mexican American People: A Generation Later, Vilma Ortiz, Regents of the University of California, 1999 August (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Rwanda - Reports and Articles, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Sudan/Ford Memos - Urgent Action on Darfur, 2004 July (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Immigrant Participation and Immigration Reform (IPIR) - National Launch Convening, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Urban Institute, 1994-2000 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Urban Institute - Assessing the New Federalism Project, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Women and Philanthropy, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- World Conference Against Racism (WCAR), 2001 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Foundations in the Newt Era, Sally Covington and Larry Parachini, National Committee for Responsive Philanthropy, 1995 September (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Refugee Consortium of Kenya - KPMG Organizational Review, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- America's Challenge: Domestic Security, Civil Liberties, and National Unity after September 11: Executive Summary, Migration Policy Institute, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Community Foundations/Intergroup Relations (CF/IR), Charles Stewart Mott Foundation and Ford Foundation, 1998-2001 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- English in the Lives of Day Laborers, Workbook Level 1, CASA of Maryland, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Human Rights Abuse Documentation Reference Manual, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 37, Box 5, Folder 38)
- Community Foundations/Intergroup Relations (CF/IR) Program - Recommendation for Grant Action Form, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- International Refugee Rights Initiative - $91,000, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- JEHT Foundation - Immigration Reports and Articles, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Kosovo Grants, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Management Assistance Group (MAG) Findings and Recommendations: Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law of Texas, Strategic Planning Process, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, Refugee Conference, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Leadership Conference on Civil Rights - Letter to Senators, 2007 January (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Migration in an Interconnected World: New Directions for Action, Report of the Global Commission on International Migration, 2005 October (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Migration Policy Institute (MPI), Doris Meissner, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Migration Policy Institute (MPI) - Verification Pilot Evaluation Workshop, 1996-2002 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Migration Policy Institute (MPI) - Background, 2001-2004 (Box 6, Folder 50)
- Operational Protection in Camps and Settlements: A Reference Guide of Good Practices in the Protection of Refugees and Other Persons of Concern, The UN Refugee Agency, 2005 December 15 (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Regional Seminar on Internal Displacement in the Southern African Development Community (SADC) Region, Gaborone, Botswana, 2005 August 24-26 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- Reorganizing the Immigration Function: Toward a New Framework for Accountability, International Migration Policy Program, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- The World in a Zip Code: Greater Washington, D.C. as a New Region of Immigration, Audrey Singer et. al, The Brookings Institution, Survey Series, 2001 April (Box 6, Folder 54)
- Transnational Economic Justice Initiative: Groups for Review and Consideration, 2007 March 6 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- US Human Rights Fund (USHRF) - Public Interest Projects: Proposals, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  USHRF LOIs for IMM
- Working Papers: Beyond Rule of Law Orthodoxy, The Legal Empowerment Alternative, Stephen Golub, Carnegie Endowment for International Papers, 2003 October (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Undocumented Students' Access to Higher Education - Activities of Ford Grantees, 2001 July 27 (Box 7, Folder 58)
- International Rescue Committee, Inc., Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children, 1997-2006 (Box 7, Folder 59)
- Declaration of the Hague on the Future of Refugee and Migration Policy, Society for International Development (SID) Netherlands Chapter, 2002 September (Box 7, Folder 60)
- Migration Policy Institute/Learning - $155,000, 1998-2005 (Box 7, Folder 61)
- Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children Publications, 2006 March (Box 7, Folder 62)
- Migration Policy Institute - $1.25 Million, One Year, 2001-2002, 1997-2003 (Box 7, Folder 63)
- Oxford-Gil Loescher, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 64)
- Rights Begin at Home: Protecting Yourself as a Domestic Worker; Los Derechos Comienzan en Casa: Protéjase si es Empleada/o Domestica/o, National Employment Law Project, 2006 January (Box 7, Folder 65)
- The New York Immigration Coalition, 2004 August (Box 7, Folder 66)
- National Immigration Law Center (NILC) - $450,000, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 67)
- International Refugee Rights Initiative (IRRI) - $90,000, Fiscal Year 2006, 2004-2006 (Box 7, Folder 68)
- Migration Policy Institute: US Immigration Reform, 2004 September 16 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  Achieving Meaningful Comprehensive U.S. Immigration Reform, January 1, 2005 to December 31, 2006, A Proposal from the Migration Policy Institute to Carnegie Corporation of New York
- Migration Policy Institute: Spin-Off from Carnegie Endowment, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 70)
- Migration Policy Institute: Demetrios Papademetriou's Paper and Bio, 1997-2002 (Box 8, Folder 71)
- Gilbert Loescher, 2001-2007 (Box 8, Folder 72)
- Migrant Forum in Asia, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 73)
- Background Reading EU Migration Learning Exchange, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 74)
- Inter-American Dialogue, Mount Vernon Inter-American Institute on Migration and Labor, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 75)
- Building the Migration Policy Institute: Year Two - $1.25 Million, 2001-2003 (Box 8, Folder 76)
- Migration Policy Institute - Preparatory/Start-up Project, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 77)
- Migration Policy Institute - Agricultural Workers, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 78)
- Migration Policy Institute - T. Alexander Aleinikoff Papers, 1998-2000 (Box 8, Folder 79)
- National Immigration Law Center - $300,000 Capacity-Building, 2001-2003 (Box 8, Folder 80)
- National Immigration Law Center - $400,000, 2004-2006 (Box 8, Folder 81)
- Heartland/Mexico US Advocates Network, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 82)
- Lawyers Committee for Human Rights - Human Rights First, 2001-2005 (Box 8, Folder 83)
- Heartland Alliance, 1997-2002 (Box 8, Folder 84)
- Heartland Alliance/Enlaces America, 2003-2006 (Box 9, Folder 85-86)
- The Chasing Freedom Campaign, Active Voice, Court TV, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 87)
- The Epidavros Project: Well-Founded Fear Film, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 88)
- The Epidavros Project: How Democracy Works Now - $300,000, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 89)
- Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 1999-2005 (Box 9, Folder 90)
- David Cole (Individual Grant), 1999-2006 (Box 9, Folder 91)
- Community Foundations/Intergroup - Memos to Lori Villarosa and Taryn Higashi, 1998-2000 (Box 9, Folder 92)
- Interpreter Releases: Report and Analysis of Immigration and Nationality Law, Volume 75, Numbers 22-39, 1998 June-October (Box 9, Folder 93, Box 10, Folder 94)
- Chrons, 1995-2000 (Box 10, Folder 95-104, Box 11, Folder 105-112, Box 12, Folder 113-118)
  Memos sent by Taryn Higashi and general grant information documents (recipient, amount, purpose of grant, nature of project, previous grants)